Guide to the Arnold Rosin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arnold Rosin papers
1937-2017
MS 1475
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11.29
31 boxes
486
The papers consist of a journal (thirty-two volumes), a notebook, correspondence, photograph album, and printed material documenting Arnold Rosin's life in Paris since 1949. Photographs of Rosin's paintings are also included in the papers.
Rosin, Arnold, 1920-
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Arnold Rosin, 1988-1996, 1998, 2000, and 2002-2017.
Arrangement
The material is arranged by accession.
Biographical / Historical
Arnold Rosin was born in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1920. He studied painting and the history of art at the Yale University School of Art. During World War II, Rosin served in the Ninth Air Force in Europe as an intelligence officer and interpreter. In 1949 he returned to France, entered the Atelier Fernand Léger in Montmartre, and settled permanently in Paris. He participated in a number of exhibitions, including the Salon de Mai in 1952. His paintings are in private collections in the United States, England, France, Switzerland, and Italy. In addition to painting and translating, Rosin worked for UNESCO, the Council of Europe, Time-Life, Le Monde, and La Vie Française. For a time he was assistant to the European head of the International Refugee Committee. In his later life, he concentrated on writing and painting. Rosin was the author of The Age of Crisis (1962) and Comment ne pas écrire un roman, (circa 2012). Rosin died on August 15, 2017.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of a journal (thirty-two volumes), a notebook, correspondence, photograph album, and printed material documenting Arnold Rosin's life in Paris since 1949. Photographs of Rosin's paintings are also included in the papers.
Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Paris (France) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Journals; Authors; Rosin, Arnold, 1920-
- Inventory
  - Correspondence, 1970-1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Printed material, 1951, 1955, [195-] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Index to journal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Journal
    - Volume I, 1951 March 27-1954 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Volume II, 1954 October 20-1956 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Volume III, 1956 September 23-1959 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Volume IV, 1959 April 2-1960 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Volume V, 1961 January 2-1962 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Volume VI, 1963 January 2-1965 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Volume VII, 1965 May 2-1968 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Volume VIII, 1968 January 6-1972 December 29 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Volume IX, 1972 December 31-1974 December 25 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Volume X, 1974 December 31-1976 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Vol XI, 1977 January 1-1978 December 30 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Volume XII, 1978 December 31-1981 January 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Volume XIII, 1981 January 2-1982 December 31 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Volume XIV, 1983 January 1-1984 March 16 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Volume XV, 1984 March 17-1986 January 6 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Volume XVI, 1986 January 10-1987 December 31 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Additional Material, 1988-1989; Accession 1990-M-059
  - Volume XVII of journal, 1988 January 1-1989 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1950, 1961-1991; Accession 1991-M-064
  General
  Includes Accession 1992-M-062.
  - Volume entitled "Notes", 1961 March 26-1990 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Atelier Fernand Léger [handbill], 1950 July 15-31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume XVIII of journal (Accession 1992-M-062), 1990 January 1-1991 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1981-1994; Accession 1993-M-078
  Includes Accession 1994-M-075.
  - Correspondence between Arnold Rosin and Helmut Meyer [literary agent], 1981 February 25-1993 February 23 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 4)
  - Volume XIX of journal [with accompanying correspondence] (Accession 1994-M-075), 1992 January 1-1994 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1994-1995; Accession 1996-M-126
  - Correspondence
    - Levin, Richard, 1994 November 4-1995 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meyer, Helmut [literary agent], 1993 March 10-1995 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume XX of journal [with index pages], 1994 January 2-1995 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1995-1997; Accession 1998-M-123
  - Correspondence with Helmut Meyer [literary agent], 1996 January 2-1997 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume XXI [with index pages], 1995 December 31-1997 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1997-1999; Accession 2000-M-106
  - Correspondence with Helmut Meyer [literary agent], 1997 December 22-1999 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume XXII of journal [with index pages], 1998 January 1-1999 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1989-2001; Accession 2002-M-058
  - Correspondence
    - G-R, 1989, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Meyer, Helmut [literary agent], 2000 January 3-2001 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume XXIII of journal [with index pages], 1999 December 31-2001 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Littérature, no. 38 [mention of Rosin as translator], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1959-1963, undated; Accession 2002-M-092
  - Correspondence/billets doux between Arnold Rosin and Lucienne Millet, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Une Histoire d'Amour" [photograph album presented to Arnold Rosin by Lucienne Millet; includes photographs and memorabilia laid in album], 1959 July 8-1963 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 1937-2007, undated; Accession 2003-M-045
  - Photographs of paintings and etchings done by Arnold Rosin
    - "Abstract Painting" [photographs of four images], 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Ann in a White Blouse" [includes sketch], "Ann with a Scarf", 2003, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Approaching Storm," "Autumn Flowers," "Azalea", 2002, 2004, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "Composition" [etching], 1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Corner of a Terrace", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "A Corner of the Luxembourg Gardens"/"Portrait of a Young Woman in a Red Sweater", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "A Corner of the Luxembourg Gardens"/"Le Vert Galant", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "The Exe Estuary/Exmouth Estuary", 2002, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Flowers and Berries", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "Flowers and Curtains", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Girl in Blue", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Green Flowers", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "July Flowers", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - "Landscape in Normandy", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Notre Dame Cathedral"/"A Corner of the Luxembourg Gardens", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - L'Orée du Bois, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Painting in the Snow," "Portrait of a Girl in a Straw Hat", 1970, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Portrait of a Young Woman in a Red Sweater", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Portrait of a Young Woman with a Fur Bonnet"/"Portrait of Lucienne Millet", 1961, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Portrait of Adriano Carallo", 2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - "Portrait of Agathe Rouy", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Portrait of Alexandre Delaplace", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "Portrait of an Old Woman", [1937-?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Portrait of Ann"/"Portrait of Ann with Long Hair", 2002, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - "Portrait of Brian Fergusson"/"Still-life", 1970, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Portrait of Catherine Delaplace", 1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Portrait of Cathy Gissane", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Portrait of Emelien Rouy" [includes photographs of the artist and subject], 2003 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Portrait of Georges Kron", 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Portrait of Lucienne Millet", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Portrait of Madame 'Vreni' Guglielmetti", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Portrait of Suzanne de Curton", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Profile of a Woman", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "Rooftops of Paris"/"Portrait of Suzanne de Curton", 1961, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Scene along the Hudson" [etching], 1946 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Seagulls" [tapestry], 1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Self Portrait" (4)/"Self Portrait with a Grey Hat", [1937-?], 1962, 1970, 2003, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Self Portrait"/"Still-life", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "Simple Flowers", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "Spring Flowers", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - "Still-life", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - "The Sunny Terrace", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - "Tapestry Cartoon", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "Terrace at Verbier", 2003 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Verbier, Switzerland", 2002 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "La Vue d'à Côté" /" Wild Flowers" /"Winter Terrace" / "Woman with a Fur Hat", 1961, 2003, 2004, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Photograph of a group of eleven paintings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Photograph of a group of sixteen paintings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Photograph of a group of seventeen paintings, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Unidentified painting [possibly done in Belgium], 1945 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Pages of photographs of paintings, 2005-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Photographs of paintings, 2006-2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 52-54)
- Additional Material, 2002-2003; Accession 2004-M-059
  - Correspondence with Helmut Meyer [literary agent], 2002 January 26-June 3 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Volume XXIV of journal [with index pages], 2002 January 1-2003 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 2003-2005; Accession 2006-M-093
  - Volume XXV of journal [with index pages], 2003 December 31-2005 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional Material, 1998-2007; Accession 2008-M-034
  - Correspondence
    - A-Y, 2000, 2003-2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Brody, Francine, 2003 June-2007 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Simmons, Jeffrey, 1998 January 23-2007 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed material pertaining to Rosin, 2004, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Volume XXVI of journal [with index pages], 2005 December 26-2007 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 2001-2008; Accession 2009-M-038
  - Art catalogs, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 2001-2002, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lannoy, Richard, 2002-2007 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Levin, Richard, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Willis, Patricia, 2002-2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 2002-2009, undated; Accession 2010-M-025
  - Art catalogs with pictures of Rosin's work, 2009 Apr, July (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, general, 2007-2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Volume XXVII of journal [with index pages], 2007 September 13-2009 May 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lists of unsold paintings and paintings in private collections, 2002-2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs of paintings destroyed or reworked, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sheets of photocopies of paintings by Rosin, 2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of unsold paintings, 2002-2008; 292; (291 JPG and 1 XML) (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
- Additional Material, 2008-2011, undated; Accession 2011-M-068
  - Correspondence
    - Barnes, Jonathan, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bernstein, Margaret, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Choay, Françoise, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - K(astolany), Françoise, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Lannoy, Richard, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Levy, Paul, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Postcards, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Simmons, Jeffrey, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Yale Office of the President, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Pierre Bergé and Associates Art Catalog, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Philosophical and philological notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Index pages: volume XXVIII and XXIX, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Volume XXVIII of journal, 2009-2011 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, 2008-2012, undated; Accession 2013-M-005
  - Correspondence, 2008-2012
    - Bernstein, Margaret (Peggy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Choay, Françoise (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kostolany, Françoise (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lannoy, Richard (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - d'Ormesson, Jean, French Academy (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barnes, Jonathan (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Brody, Francine (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bruner, Didier (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chalon, Jean (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Grimal, Nathalie (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jordes, Christine (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tanourden, Adrian (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Vergely, Barbara (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Campiche, Christian (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kavanagh, Thomas M. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Meur, Diane (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Raphael, Frederic (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Shanley, Barbara K. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Simmons, Jeffrey (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Sorlin, Pierre (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Visage, Bertrand (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Volume XXIX of journal, with chronological summary, 2011 January 11-2012 June 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Philosophical, literary, and other notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interview in Notre Temps, number 510, 2012 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 1937-2013; Accession 2013-M-063
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this accession include inventories of paintings, auction and sale price information, and material on one-man show.
  - Photographs and photocopies of artwork with related materials, 1937-2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Related materials include an inventory of paintings, auction and sale price information, and material on a solo exhibition of Rosin's work.
- Additional Material, 2010-2013; Accession 2014-M-002
  This accession consists of correspondence, a chronlogical summary of life events, journal pages, notes, and photographs of paintings by Rosin.
  - Correspondence, 2010-2013
    - Déon, Michel, 2013 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Fauvernier, Philippe, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jalibard, Camille, ADER, 2012 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kavanagh, Tom, 2012 September 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kostolany, Francoise, 2012 October-2013 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Laroche, Hadrian, 2011 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nadeau, Maurice, 2011 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Scheler, Lucie, 2012 May 13, September 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Seweryn, Elzbieta, 2013 May 26-June 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Tahourdin, Adrian, 2012 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bernstein, Margaret, 2011-2013 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Lannoy, Richard, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Marme, Romain, 2013 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Raphael, Frederic, 2012 February 26-December 8 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Simmons, Jeffrey, 2012-3013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Licht, Daniel, 2011 April-2012 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nadal, Valérie Prat, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Markesinis, Basil, Sir, 2010 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological summary of life events described in journal volume XXX, part 1, 2012 June 14-2013 June 9 (Box 1, Folder system_indicator_2a043b8b9d3acec7835d4d60c7d27a9b)
  - Journal, volume XXX, part 1, 2012 June 4-2013 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Philosophical notes, pages 28-30, Circa 2012 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of paintings, 2012-2013 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Additional Material, 2013-2014; Accession 2015-M-008; 0.25
  - Journal, volume XXX, part 2, 2013 June 15-2014 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological summary of volume XXX, part 2, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of individuals with whom Rosin interacted, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    List usually annotated with journal page references.
  - Philosophical notes, pages 31-33, Circa 2014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondents include Peggy Bernstein, Francoise Kostalany, Frederic Raphael, Joëlle Rouy, Jeffrey Simmons, and Jean-Michel Ulmann.
  - Photographs of paintings, including paintings sold, Circa 2013 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 2013-2014; Accession 2015-M-068
  This accession includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence of Arnold Rosin, spanning 2013 and 2014, as well as photographs of several of his paintings dating from 2014.
  - Correspondence, 2013-2014 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - Photographs, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional Material, 1989, 2015; Accession 2015-M-081; .25; (1 box)
  This accession consists of Arnold Rosin's journal, dated June 7, 2014-June 7, 2015; chronological summary pages; philosophical and philological notes; copies of letters; a contract to translate "Le Grand Louvre"; a partial list of translations done by Rosin; and printed images of Rosin's paintings.
  - Journal, volume XXXI, part 1, 2014 June 7-2015 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological summary of volume XXX, part 2 and volume XXXI, part 1, pages 146-150, 2013 December 15-2015 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Philosophical and philological notes, pages 14-17, Circa 2015 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 2013-2015 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
    Correpondents include Peggy Bernstein, Didier Bruner, Philippine Cruse, Philippe Fauvernier, Roger Grenier, Stéphane Maltère, Frederic Raphael, Pierre-Guillaume de Roux, Joëlle Rouy, Jrffrey Simmons, and Carolyn Williams.
  - Contract to translate "Le Grande Louvre" and partial list of other translations for "By Same Author" page, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of paintings, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Additional Material, 2015; Accession 2016-M-012; .02; (1 envelope)
  - Color photographs of "Arnold Rosin's paintings and drawings in the Ann Malnar Collection", 2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 2015-2016; Accession 2016-M-074; 1; 1 envelope
  - Color photographs of Arnold Rosin paintings, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Additional material, 2015-2016; Accession 2016-M-093
  - Journal, volume XXXII, 2015 June 8-2016 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological summary of journal, volume XXXII, pages 151-157, 2015 June 8-2016 June 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Philosophical and other notes, page 18, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Correspondents include Barbara Aycock, Frank Boivin, Jean-Jacques Faure, Joëlle Roy, John Rutherford, Amélie Sauvel, and U.S. Ambassador (invitation).
    - Bernstein, Margaret, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cruse, Philippe, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - de Roux, Pierre-Guillaume, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Maltère, Stéphane, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Raphael, Frederic, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Simmons, Jeffrey, 2015 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photocopy of photograph with Lucienne Millet, Saint-Jean-de-Luz, July 1960, 2016 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Color photographs of paintings by Arnold Rosin, 2016 January-April (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Additional material, 2015-2017; Accession 2017-M-062
  - Journal, volume XXXIII, 2016-06-07-2017-06-03 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 2015-2017 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Belmont, John, 2017, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bernstein, Margaret, 2016- (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Maltère, Stéphane, 2016- (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Rouy, Joëlle and Roland, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Decorations photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reproductions of paintings, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)